start with a line segment of length a
and cut it into two segments of length a
plus b/2 and a minus b/2 use the Aus b
over2 line segment as the radius of a
circle connecting these two points
creates a right triangle with hypotenuse
of length OT of a s + b^ S ID 2 by the
Pythagorean theorem the hypotenuse is
greater than the leg length so a plus b/
2 is less than or equal to the < TK of a
+ b s / 2 now draw this radius so that
connecting these two points creates a
tangent to the circle Again by the
Pythagorean theorem the side length here
isun of a * B so theun of a * B is less
than or equal to a plus b/ 2 this yellow
shaded triangle is similar to this
larger green shaded triangle and by
similarity that means this side length
is 2 a b / a plus b and that side length
2ab ID a plus b is less than or equal to
the hypotenuse square root of a any
choice of non- negative real numbers A
and B leads to a similar diagram except
in the case when a equals B then all the
line segments collapse to the same so we
have equality throughout if and only if
a equals B we used one diagram to
produce an inequality relating the
harmonic geometric arithmetic and
quadratic means